[Music]
hello and welcome everyone to active lab
live stream number 38.2 it's february
23rd 2022.
welcome to actin flap we are a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links here on this page
this is recorded in an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll follow good video
etiquette for live streams
go to activeinference.org to learn more
about how to participate in any of these
live streams which are part of the coms
communications organizational unit or
just any other part of the
lab all right today in active stream
number 38.2 we're going to be having our
third discussion there's the dot zero
the dot one and now the dot two on this
paper
the evolution of brain architectures for
predictive coding and active inference
and
maybe each of us have a few ideas in
mind and i'm sure we'll come up with a
few other things plus if anyone's
watching live they can write a comment
in the chat
so we'll start with just
uh introduction saying anything if we
want about the paper before just
jumping in somewhere or
somewhere else
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i will pass it to d
hi i'm dean i'm
up here in calgary and uh
i'm not
doing very much except trying to keep up
with all the papers that we're looking
at in active inference and i'll pass it
down to blue
i'm blue i'm a research consultant in
new mexico and i really enjoyed this
paper
for
many reasons the my background in
neuroscience not not
like
being a priority but yeah it is
so i'm excited to get into it and to
discuss some of the points that i picked
up with you guys
well
blue
joining us today
what figure
can we start with or
start with a blank
sheet and just any of the points that
you'd like to raise or
we can do something else
uh man like figure four for me was like
awesome um so maybe that was my favorite
figure maybe that's the one we should
start with
okay
all right
so what was your just
perspective on what figure four was and
then what did it mean or why was it
interesting for you
so i was interested in this figure and
maybe like even in
how this figure could be expanded in
terms of
hierarchical depth and temporal depth
um and temporal depth like has more than
one potential scale
um which isn't really
like mentioned here like temporal depths
can be thought of as like
small time steps like what am i going to
do next what's my next action
but also like in bigger time steps like
what is the next iteration of me and how
like these hierarchical depths like
because that's obviously like a larger
level hierarchy like the next iteration
of me as a species or the human species
right like what is the next iteration of
the species versus what is the next
action i'm going to perform as part of
the species so that was kind of um an
interesting like
perspectival
dance that they took
and just really like the the
yeah multi-dimensionality of this
um and how to kind of think about it in
like a
maybe like a
is this like a a multi-dimensional space
right like is it like um in terms of
like my cells what are myself going to
do next my tissues my organs me my
active inference lab like like what
what are all these things going to do
next and also like
on that level is that like a short time
frame or is it like a large time frame
and do the time frames differ or can
like the same hierarchical level have
more than one time frame
or or not
okay
nice questions
dean what do you
think about any of that
as we start to
look at figure four as a starting point
for talking more about what blue just
mentioned
well i think
one of the one of the things we touched
on in the point one was
the idea that within a frame there's
also an orthogonal
mesh so as we push
through this representation
from
the bottom up are we going from what
might be described as an architectural
existence
to at the top what we might describe as
architectural
learning now of course
if we take that position we have to be
careful that we're not reinforcing
the idea that it's all about
constructivism all the time
versus being creative
right like i think you need to be a
little bit of both and i'm not being
creationist like not one story that
carries forward all the way through time
as blue
kind of ref left there
but the idea that the updating
matters throughout the time
scale that you choose to look at
and so now the question is is
architecture
the lens that we should be using to talk
about how we advance from mere existence
to a place that we would describe as
learning
i mean that's what it was chosen here
but is that the is that though is that
the one way now right it's a way it's a
good way
it certainly makes something super super
complex into something that's just
complicated
but is it the only way i don't know
just um
one
question of clarification when you said
this is the only way what were you
referring to this figure four or what
through through architecture the idea of
an architecture
right the architectural lens
as opposed to other ways that we might
build out this idea of going from
homeostatic existence to going from
unknowing
to knowing
and whatever that means
okay
um thanks for sharing it just to kind of
maybe connect this you mentioned
architectural distance
which is within
the metered space
whatever the metric is or the measure or
the grids that you draw
there's
a distance within a map
and that's like the ecological transect
that's the blueprint um that's the
forensic analysis and then that's like
parametric learning because it's a
distortion of parameters in a given
space
and then
fully defined
not just like space for openness whereas
the architectural learning
is at the structural level architectural
and then that was kind of like what you
related to not just the homeostatic
or even the allostatic perhaps
but something that's like the sort of
unknown unknown
open-endedness
biological open
evolutionary trajectories yeah so not
just sustaining it but actually
realizing it so
so we'll just get a few notes like on
each of these transformations then see
what other ones or like what are some
situations that might model then also
return to the questions that were
raised early by blue like with a
multi-level self
and like where the where's mental action
or
thought in this
model
the examples were provided of like for
example with the allostat
that
took the temperature homeostat and then
added in in their example like the
sunrise visual detector and modeler
column
and so that gave the anticipatory change
in body temperature when the sun was
viewed
but then
is there a
similar structure
for cognition is it just like linking
together senses
in more and more combinatoric way
it's a very sense
oriented perspective which from an
evolutionary perspective
which is what this paper is exploring
that's the one to ground further
elaborations and changes on
rather than trying to reverse
from something like engaging encounter
factuals
so just using an active inference model
sometimes for a counter factual agent if
the model says that
that's okay or doing the bacteria
without implying that it's doing the
counter factual explicitly that might be
possible too
so we have thermal regulation in the
paper but then the question is is does
that equate to feelings in a human being
right
like it does all that that feelings
cover necessarily collapse down to the
example of thermal regulation
and at what point
are we aware of the fact that there
might be a difference between the
example
and the concept
like where in this figure four
is that is that blurry line that we
cross
it's a good it's a good question i don't
know
where it is
so dean are you talking about feelings
like emotions or feelings like
sensations or both oh yeah all of that
right like so feelings tends to take on
a big sort of
it's it's it's more detached from the
example of thermal regulation
and yet that's just the fact that you
can ask that question proves out that
maybe the one example doesn't cover all
of the different aspects
of the higher concept right
and that's where the scaling part comes
in so it's not just
it's not just temporal depth that allows
for that you have to have the temporal
depth and the hierarchical depth
what kind of feelings are you talking
about
implies that that there's
there's more than one
way that has to exist for you to come at
that
to ask that question how do we where do
we draw the partition
right
so in here
they
show duplication
but it kind of i'm not going to say it
misleads but it could potentially
mislead if you think that there's a
linearity to this
when in fact
a couple of times daniel talked in the
point one about the fact that there is a
step function moment there is a jump
it's not a jump i forget an example of
you
thought about one example where we can't
say
you just go from one eye
to two just because i think that was one
of the examples you gave daniel but at
some over evolutionary time there is
these little progressions where if you
look back on it it seems like a rather
large jump took place
right
let me give a few
points there so the when you said like
the big jumps and so
uh in one
sense that's related to the kind of
discussion around complex patterns of
evolution and some phenotypes or
genotype regions that are very stable
through long periods of time over many
generations like the ultra conserved
elements in the genome that have very
low mutation rates versus regions that
have high mutation rates etc
and then same as phenotypes like
phenotypes that are very constant like
the coelacanth fish or phenotypes that
are very
plastic or dynamic or ones that we just
don't have the records
of
um
and then how to connect what is
happening or the models that we want to
make in
humans
especially with computer enabled and
language-enabled humans
technology-enabled humans with the
continuum of
cognitive processes
and then
you said like it's not linear
that kind of
made me think like there's like feelings
which
um was still it's still a rich
qualitative area
like you brought out like sensations but
also experiences and emotions
and then
how
[Music]
quickly slash securely or um
unambiguously can we map just that cloud
of concepts just to be like it's a
policy selection on attention it's an
uncertainty on
valence
it's valence like we're doing the
parametric cognitive model
with this
but it's still even a little bit open
what this represents is this the
evolutionary biologists
doing model testing on a phylogenetic
tree
or
is this talking about the genomic or the
neurophysiological components that have
to be connected just anatomically
for a certain function to arise
and
that is the rich area that there's so
much to explore in to
well i think the one thing we can agree
on is it it because we're talking about
evolution we're talking about history so
it is backwards looking and backwards
looking is
easier than
looking into the future right
so i think that's one thing we can agree
on so what this is trying to do is
explain
perhaps how the history came about
so one thing um that the authors
mentioned as well and that's kind of
linked to the idea of feelings um you
know this was a discussion about the
evolution of brain architecture but
there's also the fact that
brains are in bodies they don't just
exist in jars
and and for me at least um i feel like
i feel
like emotions not necessarily sensations
but i feel like emotions are driven in a
large part by the body like we've we've
made a huge kind of connection between
like the gut and the brain
um
and like there's probably more
connections to be
felt
um because i feel feelings like emotions
deeply in my body like i feel them in my
heart or i feel them in my stomach or i
feel them in my pinky toe so
i i really think that the idea of like
emotions are is
can't be separated from from embodiment
um but prediction i think
it's a mental activity or at least like
i feel it in my
brain so i don't know if that's the same
kind of um
sensation that everyone has but like
prediction is
in my mind a brain thing but i know that
it's also that's overrideable like if
someone throws a ball at me like i put
my hand up like that's a reflex
so
but that's is that like my brain driving
my body
i'm not sure really but i know that
there's um you know
some prediction that's maybe not
mental that's more like physical or
that's more embodied is probably the
right word
and you kind of move into that intuitive
space as well right like if you think
about going to the beach i can't tell
whether you're going to think about the
wetness aspect of that the the warmness
part of that the the smell of the
sunscreen part of that
but you're gonna but that prediction is
gonna also
generate embodied
emotions
even though you may not articulate them
right
you're still intuiting them
you're still anticipating them and so
i'm not sure how the architecture
pulls that out especially to daniel's
point where
our
our form has adapted
evolutionarily to the to the
phenotypical situation that we find
ourselves in
and going forward
with let's say with let's say that sea
levels rise and suddenly you have
beachfront property where for millions
of years you did not how does that
affect now your emotions
right
so
i i like the architectural idea of being
able to take something and look at the
historicity of it and be able to be able
to explain it out with a little bit more
confidence
um i'm not sure though i'm still
struggling with being able to figure out
how
if we want to look ahead
we can necessarily set it up the layered
way it was set up here and i really like
figure four
so but i just have to categorize it and
keep it where it's most useful which is
in the backwards facing part of this
that's all
okay
let's return to how to use this right
that sounds like a good question but
we'll get there
so
um
lou brought up the
brain and compliment with the body and
this was just the quote from the very
final lines of the paper or near the
ends
um
where they acknowledge that
partial perspective that they present in
the paper partial meaning just a portion
of but also partial like
partial to a certain view because
they're
with a neuroscience regime of attention
and that's the contribution that was
made that helps apply to other systems
and then there's another synthesis to be
made
and this is kind of like the opening
where they just
acknowledge that cognition can be
extended and embodied and it suggests
that not all aspects of control need to
be solved by or represented
a central generative model
so it's this point that we've come to
from many different angles from like the
ecological
and the cognitive and then here from
more of a structure learning perspective
that like
the representation
whether just in the model of a system or
in the system's own self-representation
it doesn't have to be
the exact same thing
as some latent variable in the outside
world
so it's possible to have like an
effective model of climate action
without a perfectly accurate model
but that has to be understood within
like was brought up a space of counter
factuals of what could happen
from the outside world where we really
never can eradicate the total
distribution and also the introduction
of like unknown unknowns and so that's
the fundamental openness of the external
states
and the modeler's view and then there's
um
still a lot to explore with the
counterfactuals of the models
that the
system that like the agent is
can implement
but i think that
gets a little bit to how to start to use
it
in
a certain area
but
um
yeah any thoughts or what i've got a
question for you dan
i when you study dance for example and
they're foraging and they i think it's
section 8 or i forget what section that
they say foraging really really matters
i think if we're point doing this now
i think that the sort of the go forward
piece of this is now
when you started looking at ants did you
start from a position i don't know what
your background is but did you start
from a position of
sort of pulling apart the
historicity of why that thing is now
sort of laid out the way it is i know
there's a there's a
there's a piece of that that's there but
is that is that the place where most
people that begin a study start
which is kind of interesting about this
paper because it to me
um
[Music]
going from existence to learning
implies a certain history and so i'm
wondering how you sort of come at
things when you see them foraging
where where history fits
in terms of that
you gaining some understanding of what
what's happening here
as opposed to then what happens
great question
the topic is historiosity and foraging
for 400 from dean
um
blue what would you say on the topic
first how would you bring that together
what would be some important points
so um
i really liked this um idea also and i
have like a completely unrelated point
and then an unrelated question so um it
says mechanisms of memory and planning
have evolved from mechanisms of
navigation in the physical world and
some super interesting that i thought
side point was if you've ever read the
book deep work by cal newport
he talks about memorizing a deck of
cards and if you haven't read the book
read the book but um it's interesting
because he goes through a very elaborate
um
way to memorize the deck of cards and
it's through building a memory palace
and so in this memory palace um you have
like a place that you know very well
like your own house you can imagine
walking through your door you imagine
the porch the doorstep how it looks you
imagine the um you know the doorway you
know all the rooms all the closets like
you imagine going through your house
taking a tour and exploring each room in
a very systematic way so it's very easy
to memorize a route you would take
through your house like say you're
looking for a ghost in your closet or
something hiding in your house how would
you look so so you go through your house
and you um so you have this palace right
that you have in your mind and then um
he talks about uh making every card a
character right like like so you know um
the queen of hearts is you know queen
elizabeth or or something like who is
each character in the card's deck so
each
character in the card deck becomes a
character that you memorize so you've
memorized these 52 cards as people that
you know
and then and so this is an interesting
play also on the sociodynamics as well
as the spatial dynamics so each
character in the deck is the person that
you know well you memorized that 52
people correspond to these 52 cards and
you know the layout of your house so
then when you can go through the order
of the deck anybody can do it you can
repeat back the order right away so like
you go through the cards and you say
okay you know you can go through it
three or four times then you know the
entire order of the deck of cards so
this is how to repeat back the order of
a deck of cards in
like just you memorize the order like oh
there's the queen of hearts she's in my
closet and you know like all these or
who's standing in the doorway it's like
the first card right and so you know the
tour through the house and you place
these people in this spatial orientation
in your house
and so and and this is like a proven
solid way like the people that do these
kind of memory tricks use by
constructing this memory palace and i
thought that that was super interesting
um in relation to this paper that memory
and planning have evolved from
mechanisms of navigation
in the physical world and i also wonder
if there is like a social role
that also contributes to memory and
could that social role be
this kind of higher level alistar right
like we talk about the homeostat and
that's like there's no other like you've
got one time step right and then in the
other set there's other ways to kind of
modify um but how many like
like in a social component you know to
succeed in function and to actively have
memory and prediction like does the
tissue have memory because there's other
cells in the tissue does an ant have
memory because it can spatially navigate
for food and also it knows it's friends
you know like i'm sure like ants have
ways to distinguish one ant from another
and um like they're very social
creatures like i don't think that
they're they all think that they're all
the same like my cats don't definitely
don't
like you my cats know each other but
like if you showed them like a stray cat
like they'd be really upset at the stray
cat i'm sure so you know animals know
each other i'm sure ants know each other
also and so what component of memory is
also social um and that just yeah how
many points would remind me of that or
brought that to light sorry sorry
awesome
it brings up a lot of the aspects that
i get attitude now just from a
specifically anti
perspective
so you mentioned the evolutionary aspect
it's one of the themes of the paper that
perhaps from foraging but
other processes too as key cognitive
demands
those early challenges or like
ancestral challenges giving rise to
current life were faced in and met in
this way so that was the evolutionary
aspect you mentioned
and then um
thinking about the history
at multiple nested scales so like
there's the history of the ant colony
as
a genuine modelable entity
where the colony year after year kind of
develops in its foraging territory
as its colony personality or basically
phenotype at the colony level um evolve
and then uh asterisk
one
then at the nest mate level it's the
recent interactions of a nest mate that
induce it to forage
locally meaning retrieving a seed so
like there might be an ant whose current
neural or hormonal state is such that a
lot of interactions with incoming
foragers
don't stimulate more foraging but then
there might be another ant whose status
is such that
um a certain reduced rate of
interactions with other foragers maybe
even no interactions with other foragers
in the entry chamber
cause it to go on a foraging trip
that foraging biology is specific to
this ant shown here the harvester ant
but maybe other ants too okay that's
asterisk two then there's the ant tissue
and like each of the ant tissues the
brain the different glands
um the gut they're all undergoing kind
of
stereotyped transitions that are called
temporal polyethylene or they're going
through like recent changes like a leg
was lost and then the rest of the body
like adapts so that's like the history
of each nest mate tissue
the asterisks kind of combine for me
personally but also just more
conceptually
with thinking about the relational view
on modeling the ants
like not taking too
strong
a view on where
phenomena should be located in terms of
nest mate versus collective cognitive
features and then also the place based
and the field and the long-term
experiments
so
my advisor professor deborah gordon
has done like a 30-year plus field study
in arizona
and so i was doing five years of field
work there
but it was like year
i don't know 20 something or 30
something to some other number five
years later in this space
where there was a lot known about this
ant with a long-lived colony but with
turnover of the foragers
and so
the sort of
ecological and the place-based nature
and then also the specific biology of
this ant where the forager was just so
clearly an expendable part of the
process of the colony like sloughed off
kind of and some other features of the
foraging biology of these ants
pretty interesting system and it reveals
a lot on like different cognitive
demands in different foraging
environments
so that's not even getting into the
whole mental foraging or affective
component but just at the ant foraging
level
i think you brought up an important
point though daniel and
i'm not sure if people associate
architecture
with abduction
but your your advisor supervisor
whatever her title was
her 30-year window
and then where you stepped in
for your five-year window
as nested
right right you you were the you were
the one now nested within a larger time
frame so back to blue's earlier point
but you weren't historically looking
back
from the perspective oh okay here's the
evolutionary nature you are now seeing
yourself as relative to something that
had a
a greater
um time stamp
right so you walked into the party and
you had to ask yourself did these ants
come from this colony
so back to purses
quick big question of right so it's when
i come into the situation that matters
as much as if i can
induce a skyscraper or deduce how much
structural rigidity that requires right
so i think this is kind of interesting
now because
i'm not sure if we should assume like
when you were talking about the
phylogenetic trees sometimes we just
assume where we're stepping in on the
on the
on the branching
but i'm not sure we should make that
assumption i think we have to be careful
to be as you said very explicit not just
assumptive of where we come in in this
history because if we don't we can end
up thinking that this is sort of a
linear layering
that figure four when when maybe it's
more like identity
it's it's both stable and dynamic
so it's definitely related to
almost the very first comments of blue
of like
where's multi-scale identity and
multi-scale systems
in this
hierarchical depth
it may be related in some way to um
multi-scale systems we could draw that
out but where is that nesting that we're
describing the real physical enclosure
sense
and this
way that mental systems can almost be
modeled as nested just like we saw
mental action
as a nesting of a cognitive model with
an action model inside of it
it's like the mental is enclosing and
even modeling
through inclusion of the parry personal
space but then with like a drop off
going further out
and then what is that
modeling
space and
is there another operation here again
what are these graphs what are we seeing
here
dean well my question is is does it
to answer blue's question does it do do
we get closer to a satisfactory answer
by looking at the mechanics of this or
do we get a better sense of it by seeing
the relationship like when you were
explaining the ant part you spent a lot
of time talking about relationship
and i think maybe
one of the things we try to do is we try
to apply the operation to it
when and when in fact what we should be
doing is seeing the relationship
in in its entirety i'm not don't want to
say zoom out
because you can still zoom out and still
get bogged down in the sequencing
because that's kind of what this does it
says this this layer of sequencing can
now build out fractal out into these
other layers of sequencing and i'm i'm
suggesting rather than seeing the layers
maybe it's the totality of the
relationships
i don't know because blue also pointed
to the social piece
which is all relationship all the time
right
so i'm just wondering if we help
ourselves
if we if we collapse to
oh well this is now explainable because
we have
some way of
showing the sequence
sometimes that helps but maybe in this
case
it's from a from an evolutionary
standpoint
it doesn't matter whether we're talking
about a hundred thousand years ago and
today as much as the relationship of
what 100 000 years ago and today
represents
i don't know
just throwing it out there
thanks for sharing it just one thought
on that and then we'll continue here
um
[Music]
phylogenetic trees
with genomic data are usually based upon
sequence alignment
followed by the fitting of a tree on the
aligned sections of the sequences
and so there's a lot of
ways and approaches of modeling from the
sequence alignment itself from unaligned
to align sequences a lot of ways you
could do it and then from the align
sequence matrix
to
the tree model there's a lot of ways to
do that it could be a bifurcating tree
it could be like a different kind of
tree different algorithms bayesian etc
one interesting point
that
many have raised but it's very
challenging to deal with
is that depending on how stringently you
align the sequences
different sites with different histories
or different information content
partially or
in totality
are being filtered out in a different
way
so if you have a mode of evolution where
like short chunks get interchanged so
that locally the sequences are not
changed like domains of a protein aren't
changed but then they're swapped in
order
those might become non-alignable
sequences
and so the hope is that those kinds of
genomic changes are
silent with respect to the long-term
evolutionary history of a species but in
the short term other methods might be
needed but in the long term it's the
hope that by pulling back like the
alignable sections you can get a good
signal and so that's a pretty
satisfactory approach when multiple
converging threads do
overwhelmingly agree
but it really shows that when there's
like a signal processing filtering
and then a model fitting
this
the
information in the data can be extremely
powerfully misleading
because there's so much because you're
getting exactly the same
post normalized data
whether it was total
noise in
total bias out or whether your
correction process
over normalized for one thing or another
those are kind of in that gray zone
unknown unknown space
coming into the searchlight
and so there's the whole
looking out of the searchlight story so
maybe
where do we situate active inference
with respect to that
um looking where the light is
searching for one's keys etc etc
so can i just say real quick i'm not i'm
not advocating for
don't show your work
i believe that showing your work really
matters
and then when you're trying to explain
what's happening at a certain point
don't get stuck in
well this was this was the order of the
steps that i took when i showed my work
try and zoom out and try and understand
what the relationship was well that's
all i'm
what i'm
asking is that does that help
being able to to to toggle back and
forth
so
can i just jump in here for a second and
point out that we had phylogenetic trees
or we had
yeah i guess
um they weren't called phylogenetic
trees at the time but we've had like
speciation trees long before we had
genetics right and so like we can
construct them based on morphometric
analysis
and something that i liked in this paper
is that it really um
drew out the importance of the niche
environment with respect to duplication
because we saw many instances of species
because we did these trees um
when we didn't have genetic information
and so we had all of these morphometric
characteristics that we thought were
similar and so we you know lumped these
species together because they must be
related because they share this
morphometric feature but in many
circumstances that was not the case and
so because of of the similarity of the
niche environment or even existing in
the same niche you know we had evolution
converge
on this feature that was successful in
that environment and so i think here
like the idea of duplication and the
authors got into that which i thought
was really cool so so the same mechanism
can evolve more than one time
um in parallel just because of the
fitting to the niche
totally agree blue so when i said
multiple conversion
lines of evidence like what i was
totally thinking of was how genomics the
patterns that we get from those aligned
sequences
do
recapitulate and even discover
unexpected but later verified
relationships and so that's sort of like
a measure of the unique explanations and
predictions but this tree
could have been fit with phenotypic
characters as you mentioned as it was
for a long time and then it was just a
few sites in proteins and that was sort
of like the 1960s and 70s was fitting
with very reduced data sets
and now the amount of genomic data is
rapidly increasing but out of the
genomics analysis you know the action
state of
phylogenetics is really just this tree
topology fit from a family of trees
hopefully with an uncertainty
associated whether they show it like
with a bootstrap uncertainty or some
other way but then
that is an artifact now there's a few
cases where like this is in itself
interesting
like when people have resolved some deep
relationships within insects or other
groups
and then it helps structure thinking
that can later be brought out about
different traits and ecologies but it's
like
this is just a starting point for
thinking about evolutionary histories
and like you said similar
um ecological or generative processes
dynamics
might beget
increased likelihood for a certain
generative model to
arise and that's like kind of what
ecosystem is like a desert seed
harvesting ants whether it's in the
mediterranean or the southwest u.s
like pogonomyrmex in the u.s and then
cataclyphus
in them in the mediterranean regions
like there's some similarities there but
then there's other species that are more
closely related that have a different
foraging ecology
so then
how does the foraging strategy sometimes
have extreme fidelity
with the group
like leaf cutter ants where once they're
committed to being a full leaf cutter
ant
so to speak evolutionarily they don't or
they haven't been observed to
revert back to some other mode
versus other like foraging strategies at
the group level at the colony level
but it's the individual in the other
sense
that's like very interesting thinking
about foraging phenotypes on this tree
and why not
just like any other trait that you could
study like the evolution of
first spatial foraging
and then
the evolution of
cognitive foraging
and then applying that to different
search spaces which was also explored a
little in the um
citations here the um foraging in mind
and foraging and semantic fields
papers what would you say blue
well so it's cool that you brought that
up daniel and just because in our
past conversations you've brought up
that the same species of ant have can
have different
foraging patterns based upon the colony
that they live in i think that that's um
super interesting and i wonder how like
how could you
map foraging patterns like can you put
foraging patterns into a phylogenetic
tree right like is there a tree
structure that we could use to describe
foraging patterns and would that relate
to or map onto
this brain structure tree in some way
like is there i mean even i mean there's
a lot of diversity within the same brain
structure also like the ants have the
same brain structure but you know even
humans have like some of us go to the
grocery store some some humans out there
are still like hunting hunting and
gathering you know to make their food so
awesome wait oh yeah dean go for it
first
so you guys can
learn learn me school me on something
here so
is there any evidence that ants all
gather in the morning
and
the
queen ant or whatever the organizing at
the principal and pulls the map out and
says
now i want you to take this thing that
you've mapped
and carry it out today
and i'm not being a smart aleck i'm
asking is there some sort of
analogous
evidence that they
do
that
okay so to the um
uh team huddle
uh monday morning stand up
no
i hope that's not over generalizing
because ants are also of course very
diverse in their foraging strategies and
a lot is unknown
but just speaking to the first
approximation the queen is not a central
decision maker
in information router
hormonally and at a slower time scale
for sure but at the behavioral
regulation level
now
in the morning for the pogonomyrex
they would like
chill and some would
slowly come out and
like their walking speed is temperature
dependent like all insects and it just
assessing maybe the humidity or
damage around the nest entrance
so there's no reason why those
archetypes like convergence um before
planning or
rupture repair which of course cannot
have a planning component directly
different algorithms are going to have
different
levels there but because the
um
ants
symbolic behavioral communication is
pretty low bandwidth probably
so unlike the waggle dance which is
conveying like quite a lot from an
information theory perspective
using symbolic means like the direction
and the distance and and also chemical
information like about the flowers
um there's ants that like
physically pull another of their nest
mate to a foraging location so using
memory or pheromone or like tandem run
and there's probably some limited
examples of being able to do some like a
little bit higher order signaling and
also of course the smell of the food and
the pheromone and so a lot of the
extended features
um but they don't do a pow-wow with the
queen
okay so let me
let me take what you just said and sort
of feed back and maybe build on it a bit
so you described a situation it's
morning if morning then aunt behaves
like so and in the last slide of
this deck
and the phylogenetic tree you had then
to now or then if
so what i'm wondering is
can we can we exist in a sequential
world of if then
like an as a homeostatic representation
is if then all we need but if we want to
include temporal depth
and higher hierarchical depth
we actually incorporate the inversion of
that we incorporate the then if
right
so that's my question so to blue's point
earlier
where where where is
where is this
this shift or this sense of
what's going on the relationship it
might be
the discrepancy at the for the first
representation figure one the
discrepancy might be
those people that are looking at things
from an if then perspective
if this
then we should expect that from a
predictive standpoint versus the then if
perspective uh
then
then the the
the critical call had to be made as
the base runner was foraging for second
base
and a call was made now
if now a whole bunch of people
chime in about what their interpretation
of what just happened
right so again i'm not sure if that's
i'm not sure if only looking at it
frontwards and backwards as it's a point
as a sequence
is enough i think we also have to be
able to see the relationship of if then
and then if from the historical
view and i think when we do that we go
from
architectural existence to architectural
learning
okay
let me try to restate that but i've not
lost the foraging trail
so yeah if the um outcome is like um
the end point
then
that's the uh if then uh that's the if
then if the person
committed the crime you do the time
and then um
the sort of then if takes it it
precludes if then in multiple sequences
of if then and uncertainties on if thens
and then it says okay then or it's like
if then if so we're kind of
down
and then that's where the outcome is a
starting point and so that is in one
sense it's teleological because it's end
directed like where is this project
gonna go do we really expect and prefer
to publish his paper on february 28th
and then also
it includes the next steps so it creates
a world model where
there is a possible which is a
selectable set of policies that the team
will achieve like that expected and
preferred outcome and then it sets it up
for what would be the obvious next loop
of policy selection and so if it's like
if things are this good or bad with the
environment in 2030 then this is how
much damage will go to this or this way
even if you were right
it wouldn't
involve the policy selection element
and so
that's probably a complex situation with
the partitioning of like estimation and
world policy selection which is clearly
a separate discussion that's not only
being invoked here like as an example
but it just points to how those are
different components of inference and
then foraging like
an example of if then and then as if or
then if was like
sometimes
the colonies would pack their nest
entrance with pebbles
and then there'd be a thunderstorm
in the afternoon
i don't think a study has ever it's a
totally widely observed behavior with
many animals and was no exception with
harvester ants
now maybe there's thunderstorms where
they fail to make pebbles or it not
enough
and there's probably some false
positives too so we don't really know
the exact
success ratio maybe it's better than the
previous day's forecast maybe it's worse
but
it's very clear to see that the nest
mate doesn't need to have been
inheriting from its evolutionary history
and its niche
raincloud modeling software
it's just picking up pebbles with a
proclivity to interactions and humidity
etc
that help colonies that have that
proclivity succeed in that niche
which doesn't even mean that it was a
popular phenotype like 20 years ago
as things change in a region
so that's like super interesting
um
let's return to foraging
and the foraging variation question but
first let's see if we've completed the
figure four
discussion
okay and um just like is there anything
else we want to add about like the main
because this is kind of what the paper
works towards
and then there's like a little downhill
roll is like we could do this algebra on
the tree
but this is sort of where things get led
up to
through demonstration of the motifs and
the connection between cognition
and structures and structure learning
and then like parameter learning
at a behavioral or developmental time
scale
and then structure changes over
evolutionary time scales
so we have
hierarchical depth temporal depth which
we're also just kind of adding in a
spatial component
allostat
which was
um used in the paper with the
intermodality but
maybe it could be other modalities
or same
there's duplication which is kind of
like parallelization that's like adding
another nest mate or another unit to the
compound eye of a insect developmentally
and then
i is homeostasis which is being
used here as sort of the
um
base or root or ancestral case
which is referring at the behavioral
time scale to return to us to a stable
point
and then also at the more evolutionary
time scale the eye operator on the
homeostat it's like the homeostasis on
homeostasis
it's keeping the structure of that model
fixed
and then when the homeostasis at the
evolutionary time scale is open
then the structural transformations here
are like the affordances from that base
case which is what's being shown like
with the main one on the left being
broken into these
and then each of these become the prior
for each of these next ones
anything to add or we go to foraging
okay
so
great
relevant question blue
measuring foraging so one paper though
there's a bunch that are really relevant
but
um michelle lenon 2014
did a lot of literature review
and visualizations of foraging
strategies in
different ant species so
um these are like some of the foraging
approaches
like foraging archetypes
um and then
uh
categorized those into
different traits on a tree
and um
so that's an awesome work and
something that could and should be
extended and integrated with like modern
databases so that somebody could submit
we just saw this one going in a trail
and then that kind of reduces our
uncertainty about a broader model of
ant foraging because it's like oh that's
a surprising observation about this
given what we already knew about that
species for example
but how do you actually measure foraging
variation within or across the species
so
in this case
these um in figure one these are like
kind of like the structure
at one level they're like archetypes of
structure
now sometimes they probably blur within
each other like if it's two
then it's tandem running but if it's
three is it a group or is it still like
pseudo tandem running you know so it
could be a little
blurriness and also there could be
different modes
even within the same species
or like a
in a continuum between a foraging column
with like a trunk and a spread versus
like just a spread so this is sort of
like yeah
i've got i've got to like just jump in
and say like how these look like neurons
like just with like different axons and
like uh
dendritic arbors like i'm like these are
like different brain structures so i
just had to like point that out because
that's cool yeah the bottom one
definitely does
um even both of these and even this top
one too the trunk trails
and the yeah yeah so
and
and uh
let's just say that these are sort of
archetypes within a broader space
and then
within a given um
[Music]
mode
then the behavioral ecologist will tend
to make like a more specific measure so
let's just say it's a 100 a trail
forager then
having the counts to and from on the
trail
is a good measure so like in the
harvester ants they
most basically do this trunk trail on
the top
so there would be like one or two or
three
main avenues that they were leaving the
colony in for that day and then
sometimes it'd be the same day-to-day
other times it would be slightly
different
but then what happens when one wanders
off not on a trail is it still a forager
and a lot of that space
is um
really interesting but suffice to say
that once a foraging definition has been
selected like not just the class that
it's going to be but also how it's going
to be measured in that study
then there can be like quantitative
parameter comparisons like this colony
foraged at this rate
in terms of number of outgoing foragers
per minute and then its neighboring
colony of the same species was doing at
this rate so you can do like parameter
comparisons within the species kind of
at the population level and then
there might be another ant species whose
activity it doesn't really make to
compare because it's like a different
number of nest mates it has a different
foraging ecology so that's kind of where
like the structure learning
would come into play with comparing the
ants that are tending the scale insects
versus foraging for seeds versus
doing whatever else they do and then
within a species
or perhaps across a few species that
have a similar
foraging ecology it's possible to do
parametric comparisons
um
so i have a question for you daniel yeah
where does how does foraging fit
architecture
what do you
think no i'm i mean i'm not trying to be
a smart alec here i'm i'm really curious
because most architectural
analogies
result in some sort of an outcome that's
static like there's a lot of processing
that went into the outcome
but the outcome is static and i don't
think that any of the representations in
the in the frame that you're moving
right now
although the the represent the
differences
are appear as static they're they're
supposed to be representing the
something that's quite dynamic
so that's where the question of the
architecture piece
blended with evolution
might be helpful or it might be
oxymoronic
depending upon how you how you interpret
it right
so so
nothing architecture implies like
there's an architect
i don't know like in an evolutionary
sense i'm not sure like architecture is
the right word it's weird
yeah
and i'm not saying it's wrong i'm just
saying you have to be really really
careful and then what you what
assumptions you come in with based on
what you think architecture is
you're yeah you're maybe you're thinking
it the way i am i'm not saying it's
wrong i'm just saying
what baggage does that carry
when we're talking about something
that's actually quite
quite dynamic
those ants those ants are i mean you can
see the ants and the ant hill
as an architecture yes you can take a
snapshot of it
but is that what we're really talking
about when we're talking about
foraging
so what's the difference between a
structure and an architecture i remember
that
yeah
is it just
it's just semantics
yeah i think it's more than that but we
just have to be careful that we don't
we don't um
insert one for the other thinking that
they're the same thing that's what the
whole ontology exercise is about i mean
i got my mind changed okay normally i'm
the one that argues that don't don't
give somebody an owner's manual get them
behind the wheel
right they'll they'll see their owner's
manual later but in this particular case
i'm kind of going wait a second we
better all agree what we're talking
about so so here it is what's the
difference between structure and
architecture structure tends to be the
pieces and the parts of the design and
how it goes together and the finished
object
architecture defines how the final
object looks behaves and costs
by designating how design choices are
made so architecture implies that
there's some kind of agency behind the
design and that's kind of that was kind
of my interpretation of it also
okay
oh
oh okay a bunch of stuff there
that last point would like the
definition of architecture involve the
choices rather than structure involving
just the uh description of parts so
that's kind of like
the perception variational free energy
that's like structure
it also means the entire thing so it's
not just the parts it also means the
entire object yes but it still doesn't
involve preferences or choices it's
about description like perceptual
processing is and then the architectural
definition has like choices in it
and then that is what you brought to
like agency and also architecture
um
it's like a profession and an
operational approach
to modeling the process of building a
building though there's probably
theoretical
and basic
architecture and all this other stuff
okay but just a few
thoughts here on like the
engineering and designing
so i guess one ontology that can be
helpful here is
with uh bucky fuller talking about
structural integrity which is something
that has static holding strength like a
metal cube
has static holding strength um
then there's process or the pattern
integrity
which is sort of like describing the
life cycle of the butterfly in the
caterpillar like a recapitulation of
process
and that is a lot more like this sort of
dynamic systems
approach
to
organization
rather than the build it and lock it
approach because these multi-skill
systems always have things that are
turning over at different time scales
um
and then there's just so many mechanisms
that that can be modeled
by or actually occurs by like just in
the harvester ants
it's the historiosity
of that
colony over the years then the nest mate
and that day and its visual memory and
just
how many factors come into play then
every foraging trip at an estimate level
could be seen as unique and the exact
combinations will just never be
recapitulated
some of the major ones can be
explored and then controlled for or
tested for in a lab but
that's part of the
open-endedness of dynamical systems
because by changing the setting
you can study certain features
but then it's another step
that's impossible in practice
to understand how those features that
were in a different environment
translate to the first environment
so you can take the essential behavior
of the traffic jam and then recapitulate
it with the simulation the lab
experiment and all this
but it's a different thing to actually
put it into the design time
which is happening at a different time
scale than just building the skyscraper
and leaving it there but that's more
like the dynamic organism
so where's foraging on this
and i would ask where's is there a
different kind of foraging if we're
talking about
sort of the sort of the
the
machine learning type of foraging on
this
versus the
the
wet
foraging of an ant
like is that can we actually see
that those two things being quite
different in terms of how those two for
foraging types plays out or are they
do do we do we do we focus on the things
that are different about those two
things or do we focus about on the
things that are the same about those two
types of forging
blue also with your foraging from a more
cultural
and human perspective
for machine learning and foraging
so
machine learning and foraging i mean so
yeah so i've done some modeling of
foraging with like agent-based modeling
but um
in machine learning i wonder like
i mean i know that there's information
for origin but that's usually explored
from the human context right like humans
going out and looking for information
and how long we stay on the website and
whatever
so
but um
i wonder about machine learning and
like you know neural networks doing
object classification like is there a
foraging that they do there like you
know they pick up things like um
uh chris ola wrote a really awesome
publication about um
you know how we understand how neural
networks work and they kind of
deconstruct deep dream uh that's on onto
still pub which is really cool it was
like a 2018 paper but you know they look
at
how how does a neural network recognize
a dog you know and or a dog in a tennis
ball so they look for like round object
and like uh you know floppy ear like so
there's like different neurons in the in
the neural network that'll like learn
what is a floppy ear or learn what is
like a round object and so like it's
this combination of different things
that that the neural network learns
that's pieced together to form like this
is a dog with a tennis ball um which is
it's a super interesting way to think
about it and i wonder like in training
neural network
um
can that be looked at as as a type of uh
information forging right like the
network is setting out to learn distinct
pieces of a pattern that it'll later
like
piece together to to make its complete
image recognition
so
um
interesting
i'll give a
thought on the machine learning in the
and the bio foraging
so you mentioned like what's
well there's the question of should we
approach it from a similarities or a
different perspective and there's
different reasons why you might approach
different angles right like what is the
most pedagogical to someone learning
about the difference versus what is the
best way to approach this to a certain
stakeholder who is actually applying
this question in a certain context
but to get to the question outside of
that um
the idea of contrast came to mind
because we recently had the model stream
on contrastive active inference which
used machine learning so check out that
stream but it involved a contrasting
step
of processing inputs before doing policy
selection etc so that helps
scenes that are broadly similar but have
a key difference that's small like where
the ping pong ball is can be learnt
better because there's a contrasting and
that reminds me of language learning
when it's like here's
and here's
and then that's a contrast that isn't
going to come up in the language but
then it helps learn on that
and that's not just a machine learning
thing because even in the parametric
modeling
of spm
statistical parametric modeling
mapping
but the model making of it
the contrast matrix is the experimental
design
and so if it's just condition a and
condition b and you have ten
measurements it's just five of a you
know five zeros and five ones
and that's like the true or false matrix
that basically gets multiplied to do
statistics on
so whether it's a very
classical parametric
sparse modeling approach which was
initially all that
was had by statisticians or whether it
is now
things that are
highly parametric
or just all this other stuff with modern
machine learning the contrast is like
this key piece
because it's always about what signal is
being detected
within a data set and then also how the
difference between that sample
and the population is being modeled
and so like in parametric statistics
that's about the sample standard
deviation and then there's a slightly
different equation for like the
population standard deviation if you
would have kept on sampling and then
it's also sometimes hard to incorporate
that kind of a
reasoning into these more
modern statistical systems where it's
like very easy to over fit
because there's a lot of data but it's
hard to model how that large chunk of
data is related to even other segments
of data
so it's similar to the phylogenetic
challenge but that is one that is like
searching for contrast takes on a very
different meaning
but
how is it related to foraging
there's the info foraging like blue
mentioned
there's the path element of foraging
which might be related to like inferring
the best
info foraging path for somebody on their
feed
because it has to balance
the epistemic in the pragmatic or at
least it acts as if it balances the
epistemic and the pragmatic so
um
forging could be
maybe looked at in that way
um
[Music]
yeah dean
i think what this i think what this
this slide represents is broadly
speaking
not just or broadly identity um
i think we what we do is in that in that
diagram we we tend to differentiate we
see the levels because we've created the
partitions
we see the dependencies because over on
the far left we have actual blue arrows
that that show what that those
dependencies are
and then we reintegrate
right
um
i remember when i was doing my i always
come back to the programming that i was
doing but i used to say to the kids i
mean there's a there's a migration piece
to this that we have to develop which i
would consider to be the tactics which
would include foraging
and then there's a tools use
or a strategy piece which is sort of the
information
covered as change as measured which is
kind of the instrument
instrument piece
and what i kept saying to them was
you kind of need to have both
all the time you don't need to know the
difference between
something that's a migration
or an action
or a fulfillment in the sort of the
physical space
and the tools sort of the thinking
instrumental parts where you can
turn what you're seeing into these
models and these representations
and you have to kind of be able to marry
the two of them all the time you have to
be able to integrate them across
these boundaries when you're trying to
get into these professional settings now
that
that isn't a construction exercise
that's that's being creative because you
really don't know at the end of the day
how it's going to turn out
but but the but the big point that we
were trying to make was don't leave one
of those two things
behind like don't get stuck
because you can't go out and forage
don't get stuck because you don't think
you can draw the perfect representation
of the world it's just an instrument
right it's
i mean even a spoon can eventually drain
an ocean if you're prepared to spend
enough time on it so
i think that's what this representation
i think that's one of the greatest gifts
of this representation is it kind of
lays out very clearly that there's two
parts to this
how we differentiate
on different
eventually on different
duplication parallel parallelization
um dependency
predictability
preferential
time based and spatial based and then
scale based
and then
reintegrate it all back together into
some sort of a coherency
for some people though i think it's kind
of dense
i mean if you walked in today
gee i don't know what kind of
prerequisites you would need what kind
of priors you would need to understand
what the heck we're talking about
but as i said for me the the entry point
the lowest level was do you migrate
do you tool use
most people already admit they can find
examples when they do both
so my question then would be so will you
know that you're doing both
going forward and then and if you can do
that
maybe it's not quite so
quite so dense or quite so
mystifying
a few things there so
great point that
going foraging
on your merry way without having all
hidden states
learned at the structural level
or the parametric level even conditioned
on a structure so you don't even know
what's out there
no cognitive agent does
and at the structural and parametric
level
the inference challenge is about action
selection under uncertainty
of multiple types
the inference challenge
is
of action having sub problems involving
inference on perception and causal
modeling but those are like little sub
problems within a broader frame that
active inference provides of like action
orientation
action on policy selection and then
foraging is a great
setting to study policy selection
and then you brought up like that
there's prerequisites that we hope to
learn what different backgrounds can
come to active inference from but like
i think one takeaway from the paper
would be that perhaps
our cog in a forging structure
whatever that means
but the way that we forage through
linguistic and idea space and solution
space strategy space
can be modeled by some graph motifs and
classes and transformations which is
what the contribution of this paper is
and they also describe some of the more
basal or homeostatic ancestral
structures so it's like you have a
linear model that works for height data
and it works for weight data and it
works for height and weight together
it's just any numbers you pass to the
linear model the glm it's going to be
basically okay
this is like another model class
that can take
or apply to
cognitive modeling
homeostatic modeling
cognitive and homeostatic modeling
all these variations that are being
described here so that's just one way to
put it with
perhaps fewer prerequisites
and then these were interesting
questions
is this what it was do you migrate and
do you use tools
yeah
so if you're if you're doing and when
you're talking about tools are you
talking about provisions
and especially if you
if you come to breakfast with a plan
on how to build a spoon
how is that going to help you eat your
cereal
when when you're when you're foraging
exercise was to be able to move the
cereal from the bowl
into your mouth
right so lots of times especially in
some of the more
conventional ways we look at things we
tend to take the plan
to the to the cereal bowl instead of the
actual spoon
so the provisioning part is more than a
plan
it's more than the words and it's more
than the representations it's the actual
implements
that we carry with us when we do that
migration
that i think really counts because if
you carry a i guess i guess you can
origami a sheet of paper
into a spoon
but then that's another process that you
have to go through and really what you
wanted was just
to have the implement
so
so when you talk about migration
like how far
is the migration like if you're a single
cellular organism like you know
migrating through the ocean
like um
maybe the migration in that case is
moving around you right
like you don't have to be you don't
think migration in terms of me from a to
b if i'm stationary and a to b are
passing by me
like when the car beside me is pulling
out of the parking lot i feel like i'm
moving forward
right that's also a migration
so that is um
related
to what we talked about with some of the
geometry like the projective geometry
and how there's the flipping between the
egocentric geometric projection
where it's like your parry personal
space and it's kind of like a
distribution around you like there's me
in the center or located somewhere
and then there's like things closer to
the eyes are generated to be
bigger because they don't have to be
because we know we're making the
generative model anyway so why does it
have why can't i see it from grand theft
auto perspective
it is a certain way for a certain reason
so then
that is flipping
that's flipping with the um
[Music]
more like
objective
or d
personalized stance like the prior on
the architecture structurally of my room
with a right angle and even if it looks
different than a 90 degree angle in the
generative model that's perceived as
normal or unsurprising
because it's compatible
with the underlying structural
hypothesis that's unobserved and then
the observed structural observation that
has to do with the actual way that the
angles
look
so here's just one other um
uh
kind of professor gordon shout out slash
angle to look into
evolution of algorithms for collective
behavior
so
let's connect this
to the cognitive
foraging and then dean's questions do
you migrate do you use tools and do you
provision
so that's like
related questions to that one might be
like
how how do you adapt when things change
and you can't
adjust certain things or
um
also the difference between like let's
just say i'm using a software i'm not
very familiar with like
photoshop between doing one move
photoshop searching on a search engine
how do i paste okay paste okay i do one
move so it's like a one step model of
function versus someone who just rolls
out of bed
opens up photoshop and then they just
open their mind to being creative and
being in feedback with what they
actually do
and maybe that does involve still using
a search engine but they're in a
functional flow with respect to that
tool
and they've just set aside the time
so that their regime of attention can be
like productive or aligned with a
project but they're not
going step by step they're engaged in
broader
organization
so we're talking about figuring out part
rather than the finding out that's what
you just described the difference
between those two things
yeah opening space for figuring out
for figuring out
and that's sort of like um
[Music]
it's a little bit like local and more
miso or global foraging
which is like you can dig in a given
patch of dirt so it's super labor
intensive
but it's a local it finding of what is
there
versus
trying to find a better patch of dirt
and dig their first seed maybe even find
an exposed seed
but whether one of those policies is
like has a higher risk of reward or
energy expenditure that's going to
depend a lot on what one believes about
the frequency of like
half emerged seeds and seeds in this
location and the time cost of moving
from location to location there's just a
ton of features and it's not just like
as simple as making a heat map of where
the seeds are
we
would describe it as mimic foraging and
and and
mimic foraging and what was the other
one
modify
foraging
some people might oh blue go for it
so it's interesting at the um conference
i was at last week the you know they
talked about like how far can you get
mimicking an expert and there are
several like talks like so you know
whether it's
navigating a maze or or you know
figuring out whatever so like you know
they'll train a model on a whole bunch
of expert what would an expert do
and then they set them loose in like a
novel circumstance and if the novel
circumstance is similar enough it kind
of works but but really like the better
thing to do is to put some exploratory
component in there so you know you have
like the expert training but but if
there's an explorer component
about that doesn't have to do with an
expert or like you know if we train it
to navigate its own maze also sometimes
like alternating with its own maze or or
you know
amazed with experts in it so like
following the experts only gets you so
far and i wonder um
and something that's come to really mean
a lot to me in the field of intelligence
is like when
it's it's when there's innovation like
when you can do something new when you
can generalize and solve any maze
because you learned from a few experts
like that's innovative or you know like
the ability to generalize but also the
ability to innovate and produce some new
output rather than just do what the
experts do
so
one
thought that's awesome comments blue
like
learning from examples and from experts
usually learning by example when used
not in a malicious way is referring to
seeing somebody who is better or at
least adequate if not
far far better
and then there's this question of like
should it be shown only at the expert
level
because the
expert speaker would do tongue twisters
and
russian sentences with five conjugations
but the
expert in interaction
is able to approach a zone of agreement
and of like proximal development
so that the example and the expertise as
applied
is in a very specific space
and that's like the order of examples
and then knowledge like this person is
able to conjugate this thing but they're
having challenging conjugating this case
so then
depending on their personality maybe you
lean more on the one that they are more
familiar with or maybe they
come to you to be wrong so
there's a lot of
advanced cognitive modeling and
parameters that could be in a
full-fledged model because that's a
super complex scenario especially in a
group and all of these you know
relationships on
relationships and
we don't need to have that whole
generative process model
to have a generative
model of policy
that can be effective at foraging in
that space
so it is a project
and
making that map is helpful for it
but to make policy decisions in the
cognitive space
isn't the same as describing and
mastering all the variables of the
cognitive process
and so this mental foraging and physical
foraging and also what we talked about
with a sensory motor detachment
helps make that really
clear
so like
how does
active inference model
relevant expertise
whether domain expertise or discipline
like
a set of affordances a versus a whole
different set of affordances you know
maybe
or expertise like in that language
learning example or some other example
where it's not simply about like
providing some
advanced example
and then having people asymptotes of
that
it's about opening the space for
figuring out
in that setting
i think you can find a structural
adaptation in mimicking an expert
and and that that typically sort of
plays itself out as instructionalism
i think you can find yourself also
modifying your niche and adapting in
that way
and then being able to go back and have
an expert
look at what you've done
and the reason why they're an expert in
that particular case isn't because
you're going to mimic them
but because you're going to ask them
what they
how the process that they use to arrive
at where
they have a certain subject
confidence
they are able to now diagnose
where your where your confidences
might
exist and where you might
want to
might want to re-examine what the
probabilities and preferences were that
got you to the conclusions that you drew
so
again
you're going to adapt either way
but i think that the the path that you
choose matters and knowing which path
that you chose also matters so i adapted
right i adapt because i i'm now trained
up to be able to
find the the blue dot the blue ball in
the
the sea of plastic balls right
that that's one form of of adapting
because
i've never been in a ball pit before and
now i found the one that i was looking
for
but the other but another person could
go in there and be able to
maybe
do something else with that blue ball
because they modified the frame and the
mesh and
that's
that again
we just want to make sure that we know
that there's a difference so that when
we are reintegrating them at some point
in the future we know how we got there
that's all
okay
i like the
throwback
to instructionalism and interactionism
it's an example it was like latently
there when talking about that
niche dependence and the co-creation so
all these kind of terms
digital sigmoidy when working online for
example become implicit
when we're using a given
sequence to be talking about like a
certain thing that we want to call our
attention to we call our attention to
some example
or to some relationship
and then that modifies our cognitive
model
so that we're thinking about things and
doing things differently
after
and so it's kind of like quality of
engagement
rather than quantity
because
some people by
reading a little
change a lot and vice versa
it's how you set up the relationship i
think
it's funny that you bring up um
reading so like for a very long time um
my my phd advisor like never read
anything like she would never read
anything did you oh yeah
but like
she just she does like speed reads she
speed reads right which means like she
looked at every third word
and then like when she really sits down
to read it she's got all these things to
say about it and wants to like you know
word smith every sentence and um it's
great like we've had a lot of fun
working together i don't i don't mean to
like make that sound evil in any way but
but i mean i i don't speed read i read
fast but i i i'm totally incapable of
speed reading because i feel like
i have to duplicate my efforts like if i
skim it like i can you know pick up some
key you know headings or whatever but
but i never really
got to read it like like i want to read
something i want to really read it like
go through it line by line by line and
look up things i don't know what they
mean and this kind of thing so so it's a
different
um an interesting approach how different
people approach things in different ways
yeah
yeah you know
talking about
in this paper
how we've been going between the sort of
physiological and biological
substrate of cognition
and the nervous system and the brain all
of that and then this more
cognitive modeling approach which can be
sort of cut and dry or overly
computational or so-called unrealistic
with respect to biological foundations
it's kind of like what dean pointed to
with like the bifurcation and so now
things are kind of
coming together
not in the way that everyone might have
expected but at least in a way
and so that's a very
um
interesting space and then like blue
with a fast and slow reading
it's almost like
there are multi-scale dynamics
associated with attention
that can be measured with the eeg
but it's a hidden state what is actually
happening in the mind and brain but
those are the kinds of experiments that
people use and there's some rhythms like
the fast cycles like gamma that are
playing out at like kind of like the
speed of perception
and awareness of like words
and then there's also slower like
symbolic or semantic
changes and all these different time
scales and it's just like
making the space to let
the connections and the terms
and the implications resonate
and connect with the learner and the
creator
is like a lot more valuable than any
amount of
coefficient of low
reading
and so how to balance the information
amount
and type
and sequence and all of these things
with
holding the space for just the slower
transformative process
and that's very related to
yeah that's that's huge daniel because i
think a lot of people that they get into
the um
instructionalism you'll hear the
expression and i'm not i'm not over
generalizing here you'll hear we'll
we're going to break this down
as opposed to the the interactionism
which is we're going to slow this down
there's a there's quite a difference
those two things
open up and slow down or
we're going to
drill down finish it out get it done in
the time
and
as we discuss like
this is the archetypes or the dialectic
it's not like we're only taking one
approach or another but it's very easy
to see how the range in
at least education space not even
thinking of other areas
is like
it's the amount of content and then it
projects down into
how it's delivered
and then content gets slotted in or out
or things get expanded or not or the you
know monday's class gets canceled and it
moves to tuesday
so that's like the sort of instruction
projection
approach
which is so different
in multiple ways
especially in how it's applied to
thinking more about the opening up of
space and slowing down
and the learner's journey and all that
and when you're in the huddle in here
and you're calling out the shorthand
before you actually line up at the
scrimmage line and snap the football
it's interesting that what you pointed
out blue i
in my history i was always wait prepared
to slow down when it was math and the
symbology
like i have no problem slowing down for
that but trying to read out long
sentences
it just about kills me i mean
my add i can't i have to interleave like
every every 20 to 30 minutes because if
i don't
my skin starts to crawl so i mean those
sort of contextual
factors that are literally weighing on
you
you don't know those sorts of things and
if you're an expert who's just trying to
push out all this information in a
13-week window
i'm not really sure whether or not you
can sort of get down to that level of
personalization but if you're
if you're able to
it makes all the difference in the world
in terms of what people take away from
from the uh exposure right
i find it way easier to do the shorthand
thing i i you know if a picture's worth
a thousand words
i'm i'm in full agreement with that
i just can't do the thousand word thing
so
yeah
yeah really interesting and steven wrote
in the chat good to see these questions
about active modeling
expertise
being thought of in different ways like
the direction of travel the distance to
travel the rate of travel mode of
transport
yeah thanks for sharing it stephen um
landscapes and sort of the sense making
and the wayfinding
and being on this
cognitive landscape versus or and being
on this spatial foraging landscape so
going out for the mushroom forage
with someone who's familiar with
mushrooms and somebody else who's
familiar with the biochemistry but
hasn't seen the mushroom
in the ground
and then someone else who's on a
different perspective because of their
background or people with different
physical abilities and knowledge in the
spatial setting
and then there's
the cognitive foraging
and then
just like is it that the colony forages
as a unit
and then that's the sort of flip side of
the nest mate's forage collectively
and so the team
forges as a unit collectively
and the individual is sort of engaged at
this level that we have
experience at
in the policy selection relevant to our
participation in
some
either niche or team or project
[Music]
let's
go back to the paper see if there's any
other pieces like that we could kind of
look at
let's look at the roadmap
introduction we talk a bit about the can
we talk a bit about the endowment part
of this
we haven't really touched on that well
just the endowment what's the endowment
so in the point twos
essentially that's
now that we've built built this this
base this stable platform
what can we do with it like what
leverage have we now potentially
achieved so what's the endowment here in
terms of
what they what the paper really
what's the new affordances that we
didn't have before we them that we
didn't maybe necessarily have
explicated quite so clearly prior to
reading the paper
maybe that's one i don't want to
put pressure on but
what do you think blue
so i'm trying to remember maybe you guys
can remind me in this figure oh wait
wait wait
so endowing with with temporal depth um
it's got to be an avo step right is that
correct yeah
yeah um because in having a homeostat
with temporal depth like
isn't possible right or or like isn't
like they just can they can only do
um
and i wonder if that's like you know a
single-celled organism can only like do
at that moment like they're not planning
for it to get cold later or something
like that um
and really the
so i wonder if it's not only
temporal depth but any kind of
relationship like i wonder if it's not
necessarily temporal depth if time is
flat
right
i mean i guess in order to modify your
own behavior or thought you would have
to have some temporal depth
but but this allostatic um
idea is interesting with respect to
um you know my relationship to
my future self or my relationship to my
previous self or my relationship to
other people in my community or or
whatever
um
so i just wonder
about
if if that's why this is the allostat
and not the homeostat or like can you
endow a homeostat with temporal depth
and get that same kind of
ability for perspective and
retrospective inference like you can't
but why not like maybe let's let's put
some words to that
let me see if i can find some in the
paper
nice point
i would say
homeostatic function
could be in a model with memory or
anticipation like the thermometer could
record the last 100
time points or it could have a
prediction for the next 100
but the function would be that it only
turns on the heating once it gets too
cold
so it still is the um on the action
selection side
it still is making a one markov chain
decision
based upon an instantaneous
measurement and so it can be implemented
whether just for a computational
parsimony or in a simple biological
system with just one time step
if it's this hot then turn on the
cooling
and um so it's the ultimate if then
because it's like a threshold model
and so
it gets paired down over evolutionary
time but then you're bringing up like to
even engage with a counterfactual
or some influence of something on future
policy there has to be like a depth
and then this gets back to whether it's
modeling the thing itself like
what
do these represent are they
the scientist testing a model of one two
three or four five hour temporal depth
for the ant forager
or is this the foragers cognitive model
as if that were somehow not model based
science
or is it the neuro architecture or the
functional anatomy
of the forager
there's a lot of ways it could lean or
be framed um
[Music]
i think in a complementary
way but one will have to be really
careful where support for one domain
super valid and where is one not
like if it were a circuit board with
that topology then it seems like pretty
good to go to use that as
a pretty broad descriptor of a system
whereas if this was a simplification of
memory
and there was an uncertainty parameter
labeled
uncertainty or anxiety like we discussed
a little earlier someone slaps a
parameter on one of these edges
and starts addressing
complex real world settings
how does that exactly work
so one of the things that i think that
it endows us with is that
the homostat homeostat is the sort of
the basic the basic pattern
there's a there's a partition between
the epsilon and the mu
so the first thing that they did is they
created a sort of horizontal partition
and then when they went to the
parallelism now there's two epsilons and
two muse and so now they added the
vertical partition
as well
and i think that's really really helpful
in terms of
at the basic level of of the statistical
we talked last time that you have to
kind of be a polymath
but i think from from a modeling
perspective it's getting that orthogonal
mesh established
that moves us up the chain of complexity
because then all of a sudden you can
have diagonal dependencies
and then you can actually add the the
zed plane
going through this in terms of how the
scale is built out on both
distance and time so i think that's one
of the endowments that it provides
i could just restate that it's like when
we say that one of the advantages
potentially in application of active
inference could be that models are
composable
so
they can be composed within
a given scale like spatially or
temporally
and that has a visual
representation
it can also be composed in this nested
way which as we've explored several
times can represent physical enclosure
or temporal enclosure as well as this
cognitive architecture like mental
action
depending on how different variables are
interpreted in nested modeling
and so it's composable
in several dimensions of transformation
which they represented in figure four
in a way where each transformative step
even though the function might change a
lot from the beginning to the end
each
organizational or structural
architectural cognitive step or
morphological if one is looking at that
layer
can be mapped into
a certain space and
direction of movement within that space
do you think it can also be sculpted out
i mean because we're looking at this
historically we're looking at all the
things that happened in the history was
this the stuff that was kind of carved
out
and saw a lot of the stuff that doesn't
matter removed
in order for it to be more
comprehensible
because i agree with you it can be
composed but i also think it's not
decomposed but i do think or even
deconstructed i think it can be sculpted
out of a greater history a greater whole
this
oh yes please
so sorry like what um
you know when you talk about a greater
history and we've talked about
historicity in
in today like during in the last two
hours um
and we've also talked about memory and
there's a difference right like so so
historicity is like
historically accurate
and memory is like what
i remember or like what any
what any individual um
remembers
yeah we've talked about that before
actually i have a few live streams ago
all i'm thinking is is that what this
does is compare all the things that what
what is it axel constant that said
how did he frame it so that we can
understand why we're here now versus the
all the things that didn't make it
right
that's essentially what i'm talking
about in terms of explaining
right they're explaining why something
got to the place that it did as opposed
to
the the necessity of all the things you
had to do
all the things you had to compose in
order to realize
the outcome i'm trying to
bring that back to a sculpting metaphor
now
awesome so that's um the axle constant
2021 paper the title was the free energy
principle
it's not about what it takes it's about
what took you there
and so
that's definitely an evolutionary
perspective and it's
partially because of axel's background
in evolution in ecology because
that's what we can say about evolution
this is what got birds here
right
and so the counter factuals in evolution
are a really interesting topic and
that's sort of um
explored in a variety of like
more popular as well as more
mathematical treatments like how do we
go from the observed
which must have existed so it's very
easy to fall to them being the best of
all possible worlds optimal form etc
but then we also recognize the changing
environments and interactions and all
that and then
blue like with the histo historicity
facts and the impacts which are like
facts that aren't known
and then there's the memory which
requires a perspective
people could use system memory or
something to refer to to a fact or an
impact on a system that but these are
just being used loosely like some parts
of how the past influences the present
in the future have to do with systems
that take a perspective
other impacts are
not through those
adaptive active inference agents
and so that's very different and so
historicity is kind of like the
stigmargy pheromone layer
and then there's like memory with the
forager so you could talk about the
memory of the ground for the pheromone
but it makes sense to just remember that
it's a different thing with the
pheromone on the ground
than the cognitive infra ant
and
no nestmate is going to have all the
knowledge or the onboard modeling to
make
decisions save for the ones that
not to complicate it too much but it's
stuck in the dialectic between doing
exactly what worked in the past
which is to say recently succeeded but
might not work in the future
and changing things but once you move
into changing things
the space of the adjacency of changing
is sometimes like
daunting and you still haven't really
addressed the problem of changing world
so
forging is a very
deep entry point like into a lot of
these
questions in active inference and in
other areas because it really connects
to the
egocentric
hopefully not in the um solipsistic or
narcissistic sense but just in the
way-finding sense-making
paradigm
that actually accommodates for
others
through modeling them explicitly and
prioritizing the environment and things
like that
so
pretty
cool
and this paper just to kind of
restate what they
brought to the picture
they looked at evolutionary time scales
and they framed cognition as
structural change
which in a bayesian modeling framework
is sometimes called structural learning
as opposed to like parameter learning
fine tuning given the model structure
and they connected that to the
bayesian graph
model of the active inference
partitioning
and then connected that to the factor
graphs
and then using the homeostat example
talked about how there could be like
elaborations
into
other structures so from structures to
each other
that might be enabling the rise of
phenotypes or enabling the modeling of
phenotypes
that are interesting
okay any
final thoughts or like where does this
paper take us
what is different now what are we going
to be talking about soon
so i'm excited to um
really delve into the math that is going
to
get behind
the models that were elucidated out in
figure
4.
how do we go through time and through
relationality and
hierarchical dimensions and so forth
okay thank you blue dean you won't have
the last word but what do you think
well i'm still trying to figure out how
this sort of ties in with the whole
identity piece i i i left that because i
thought that was just a rabbit hole that
went way too far and too deep but i know
that when you do get that parallelism
and when you can sort of
create
a dimensional grid that has negative
space as well so like you can be
as units going positively or negatively
and passing through zero and how that
fits with identity that's that's sort of
that's a kind of a personal thing that i
got to do and then the other thing
that i really but with the thing i
really liked about this paper is that i
think it took something that's really
as you said over over huge time scales
and sort of
took it
took it back down to something that
that might be digestible for a lot of
people that otherwise they kind of go
okay so here's a hundred thousand years
ago or a million years ago or whatever
from the bacteria to now
what what
what are the sort of basic building
blocks
that we say might have
might have
played a part in
getting to the kind of sophistication
where we are now and again i think it's
about learning i always think that
evolution is about learning
um and so
as i said in the point one i this this
affirmed a lot of the stuff that i think
we need to be bringing into some of the
more formal ways that we struck for
learning because i think it is i think
it's learning sort of
unleashed as opposed to all tied up
awesome
thanks both and everybody who is uh
helping in all the ways for the previous
videos just some last thoughts would be
like from both of you
and hopefully all together
there's really some interesting insights
into learning and education for active
inference learning which is kind of like
our meta regime of attention in active
inference lab
when we're in that regime of attention
but
many people have other regimes of
attention where
it would certainly apply to
bring some of these methods and ideas in
and also bring
pieces from
outside into our
cognitive modeling of attention and
collaboration and communication like
those topics and how those are the
pillars of education and research
during a time when
education and research and participation
are evolving
is some of the most interesting things
and so to be able to
read evolutionary
papers
that take a cool
scope and approach
and then connect it to
how we're hopefully organizing together
and including the affordance to
participate with anyone who's listening
now
it's an interesting mixture so i hope
that we all
can just keep on learning and applying
together
all right
peace
thanks guys thanks again bye